#### **CURRICULUM VITAE**

# PENINA KAREAUKI MUTUA

P.O BOX 2-00202 - KNH-NAIROBI

TELEPHONE: +254720845961

E-mail: kareaukipm@gmail.com

# **PERSONAL DETAILS**

**Date of Birth**: 03/06/1977 **Marital status**: Married

**Religion:** Christian

Language fluency: English, Kiswahili, Kimeru and Kikuyu

# **CAREER OBJECTIVE**

To enhance food safety and safeguard human and animal health through training and imparting knowledge, skills and attitudes to the training personnel and creating awareness to the public.

# **RESUME SUMMARY**

I am a veterinary surgeon, holder of a Bachelor of Veterinary Medicine and Masters in Veterinary Public Health, both from The University of Nairobi. I am registered with the professional regulatory body-Kenya Veterinary Board and also a member of the Kenya Veterinary Association. I have vast experience in training of personnel in meat industry specifically on Veterinary public health and food safety. In addition, I work with farmers, giving both professional and technical assistance and advice in matters of animal health and management.

# **EDUCATION SUMMARY:**

# 2017: University of Nairobi

Master of Science in Veterinary Public Health (MVPH)

(Awarded a degree)

# **2013:** Kenya Institute of Management

Diploma in Business Management

(Awarded a certificate)

# 2002: University of Nairobi

Bachelor of Veterinary Medicine

(Awarded a degree)

## 1995: Nkuene Girls Secondary School

Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education,

(Attained Grade B plain)

# 1991: Kamatungu Primary School

Kenya Certificate of Primary Education

(Attained 406 marks)

#### **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY:**

#### 2013 October to date:

# Trainer - Meat Training Institute- (Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock, Fisheries and Irrigation Responsibilities:

#### • Preparing training materials and schemes of work

This is to ensure that the training materials are regularly updated to meet the training needs as per the requirements by the industry as well as the regulatory bodies such as OIE and WTO.

• Instructing and guiding trainees

This involves delivering the knowledge, skills and attitudes to the trainees through demonstrations, coaching, mentoring and other possible methods. The aim is to produce highly qualified individuals who will provide workforce and solutions to the meat industry.

## • Setting, marking and moderation of examinations

This is the assessment process aimed at evaluating whether the trainees are gaining competence in their areas of training. The assessment targets the knowledge, skills and attitude of the trainees in specific areas of training.

# Mentoring trainees on internship and industrial attachment

The aim of this is to ensure that the trainees are able to demonstrate competence in various trained areas and that they can confidently and competently work in the industry.

#### • Disease surveillance

While taking the trainees through the practicals in meat inspection, various disease conditions are encountered and related data collected which aid in disease surveillance. The data is used to guide in developing and establishing prevention and control measures for such diseases. The trainees also acquire the knowledge and skills to enable them work as agents of change in disease surveillance while in the industry.

#### Additional responsibilities

- Curriculum development
  - ➤ I actively participated in carrying out training assessment needs for MTI courses.
  - ➤ I coordinated the group involved in development of various curricular for MTI, six of which have been approved by CDACC
  - ➤ I am trained in Competency Based Assessment (CBA) in the National team and have participated as a facilitator and a team lead in various CBA trainings both at the regional and institutional level
- Staff Performance appraisal
  - ➤ I am assigned to supervise and appraise three Staff at the institute
- The dean of students
  - ➤ I serve as the Dean of students and am in charge of guidance and counselling department at the institute

e-mail: kareaukipm@gmail.com

➤ I coordinate and invite guest speakers for awareness creation in various cross-cutting issues both to students and staff.

# **March- September 2013:**

District Veterinary Officer Kajiado North District

## Responsibilities

- Coordinating administrative issues in the veterinary department to ensure smooth running of the department
- Coordinating disease control and surveillance activities at the district level to improve on animal health thus minimize incidences of zoonotic diseases
- Coordinating Veterinary Public Health and Hygiene activities within the district. This involved inspection and licensing of slaughter premises within the district so as to enhance hygienic standards and consequently minimize incidences of food borne diseases.

#### 2009-2013:

Veterinary Officer (Hygiene) Kajiado Central District

# Responsibilities

- Participated in inspection and licensing of slaughter premises and meat containers and carriers to enhance public health and hygiene standards within the district
- Involved in disease control and surveillance by participating in vaccination campaigns, clinical as well as extension services
- Assigned to supervise and appraise the staff within the district
- Participated in training of the Community Disease Control Committees in the district (in collaboration with NGOs like Neighbours Initiative Alliance) to enhance rapid disease reporting and subsequently minimise disease spread through quick response by animal health personnel

#### 2008-2009:

Veterinary Officer-Agricultural Sector Coordinating Unit attached at the District Veterinary Office in Naivasha

#### Responsibilities

- Disease surveillance and control through participation in various vaccination campaigns
- Offering professional and technical assistance and advise to the farmers

e-mail: kareaukipm@gmail.com

#### 2003-2007:

Lead veterinarian in various Agro-vet shops

# **Responsibilities**

- Selling of agrochemicals and veterinary drugs and products to the farmers
- Disease surveillance and control through vaccination and treatment of clinical cases
- Offered professional and technical assistance and advise to the farmers

# OTHER RELEVANT TRAININGS AND WORKSHOPS

2019:	Competence Based Assessment TOT course by TVET/CDACC	
2018:	Workshops to develop CBET Curricular for the Meat courses by TVET/CDACC	
2018:	Training of Trainers (TOT) course at Kenya School of Government –Embu	
2017:	Competence Based Education and Training TOT by TVET/CDACC	
2017:	Grain processing and inspection technology for developing countries by National	
	Research Institute of Food and Fermentation Industries - China	
2017:	Senior Management Course at Kenya School of Government- Nairobi	
2015:	Brucellosis incidence study for both human and animals by KEMRI-CDC, MOPHS and	
	MOLD	
2015:	Training on Good Clinical Practice by KEMRI-CDC	
2012:	Brucellosis Sero- surveillance study for human and animals by CDC, MOPHS and	
	DVS	
2010:	Training on Livestock emergency guidelines standards (LEGS)	
2009:	Training in safe poultry production by FAO and DVS	

# Registration with professional bodies

- Member of the Kenya Veterinary Board (KVB)
- Member of Kenya Veterinary Association (KVA)

#### Hobbies

- Reading educative materials
- Networking
- Participating in voluntary work

#### Referees

Dr Salome Kairu (Wanyoike)	Dr Evans Muthuma	Dr Grace M. Munyoki
Principal, Meat Training	Department of Veterinary	Cell: +254710291615
Institute	services	Email:
PO BOX- 55-00204	KABETE	mwelumunyoki@gmail.com
ATHI RIVER	Email:	
Email: principalmti@gmail.co	evansmuthuma@gmail.com	
Cell: +254722568510	Cell: +254722885183	